So, here's what we're going to do. I'm
going to tell you about something that
you can do to get your body fat to
secrete a molecule and that molecule
will positively affect your heart. It's
a roundabout way to improve heart health
and it's a fascinating new mechanism
discovered in this study discussing an
incredibly intuitive sounding molecule
called 1213 diehome. And my name is KL34
apartment Z. Honestly, the naming is
getting a bit ridiculous. So if we look
at the amount of this molecule 12 13
diehome in young and old individuals
you'll notice that the amount is reduced
in the older folks anyone over the age
of 65 and considering heart function
diminishes with age it might be
reasonable to see if both decreasing
might be tied to one another.
Spoiler alert they are. To be clear
there's more experiments that I'm
skipping over but ultimately the
relationship was realized. Older
individuals have worse heart function
and that tracks with reduced blood
levels of this molecule 1213 diome.
Still there's plenty of things that
increase and decrease with worsening
heart function. For example, insulin
resistance, uh, weight, back pain, dad
joke frequency. So, how do we pin 1213
diome directly to this heart function?
Well, how about we just inject some into
our veins? Well, that's what was done.
But don't worry, it won't be what we'll
need to do. So, when old mice are
treated with 1213 diome, we see
improvements in something called
systolic and diastolic function.
Essentially, it's the ability for your
heart to contract and relax to pump
blood. If these improve, your heart
function is generally better. In the
graph, the 1213 dihome is on the right.
And if the bars go up, that's
interpreted as an improvement in heart
function in this context. We'll return
to this because there's an important
piece of information that we need to
cover. But for the time being, we're
seeing aged hearts function better when
exposed to 1213 diehome. So the point
here is that we've eliminated all other
factors. 1213 dihome directly improves
the function of an aging heart. Now the
next questions are how and how can we
use this to our advantage without
sticking ourselves with a needle. So I
did mention that this hinges on your
body fat, not your heart. And that's
because 1213 dome is a lipocine, meaning
that it's a molecule produced and
released by your fat cells primarily.
Essentially, your fat cells convert a
fat molecule called linoleic acid, an
omega6 unsaturated fat, into 1213
dihome. And once created, it's secreted
into the bloodstream. From there, it
interacts with a series of cells in your
body, including cardiac or heart cells,
and protects them from problems that
arise from aging. things like what's
known as the endopplasmic reticulum
stress which can cause cells to
malfunction in the heart. This is not a
good thing obviously although I suppose
that could also be said of anywhere in
the body. Overall the takeaway here is
that 1213 diehome improves the function
of the aging heart by reducing stress
within the heart cells among other
mechanisms. Okay then what do we do to
stimulate 1213 diehome in our body?
Well, there are a few things that we can
do actually. One way is to increase your
brown fat activity, which is a type of
fat tissue that is quite metabolically
active, meaning that it produces
hormones like lipocines that we've been
discussing, and uses more energy. In
fact, many of the experiments in this
paper that we've been going over look at
brown fat specifically and confirm all
the effects that we've been going over
on 1213 dhome. We can increase the
levels of this beneficial brown fat in
our body by doing things like cold
exposure. And with cold exposure, there
are studies that indicate increased 12
to 13 diehome in humans as well.
Interestingly, this study suggests 1213
diehome also stimulates brown fat
itself, meaning it might be produced
elsewhere as well, like muscle. So, cold
exposure like icebass and even more mild
exposures stimulate brown fat in 1213
diehome. If you're looking for a
step-by-step protocol, I have one
outlined in my protocols page along with
more on exactly how 1213 diehome affects
our heart and an alternative method of
raising 1213 dhome through nutrition
which I detail in the extended version
of this video that you're currently
watching. The protocol and the extended
analysis plus accompanying article are
included for the physionic insiders if
you're interested. The link to join is
in the description. Plus, you get all
these perks right here which is just
more incentive if you needed it. Either
way, the link is in the description. I
hope to speak with you over there.
Another way of raising 1213 diehome is
through exercise. In fact, it doesn't
take much. As little as 40 minutes of
endurance training at about uh 70% of
your heart rate reserve is sufficient to
almost double 1213 diehome. We also know
that exercise as a whole promotes many
heart benefits. 1213 diehome promotion
may fit right into the many different
ways that exercise benefits our heart
health even as we age. The takeaway here
being that if you exercise not even
overly intensely or if you undergo
regular cold exposure, you are raising
your 1213 diehome blood levels. Of
course, considering the origin of 1213
dhome from omega-6 fats, it seems
reasonable to just consume more of these
fats, the linoleic acids. However, there
is currently no good evidence this
actually works. So, we can't say with
any certainty that's true. We'll see if
that changes in the future. But I also
did mention that we'd be returning to
these data because while we focused on
the right side, the 1213 diehome, we're
comparing against 910 diehome, another
lovely name. The researchers use 910
because it's similar to 1213 diehome,
but doesn't have any positive effects.
As far as I could tell, they didn't go
into much detail beyond that. And yet,
the literature on 910 diome is mixed
with some of it showing negative effects
while others find positive effects and
relationships. What I'm trying to say
here is that I don't think that 910
diehome is an ideal comparison
condition. They probably should have
added another control condition. That
critique stated there's still other
evidence that 1213 diehome is still
beneficial to the aging heart even if
these data are weaker. In addition,
single injection of 1213 diehome didn't
seem to do much to blood levels. And one
reason for that is because 1213 diehome
stays in the blood for a very short
period of time. So a single bout of
exercise or doing cold therapy every
once in a while probably ain't going to
cut it. You'll need to stick to it to
reap longer term exposure for
yourselves. Finally, a last point that
I'd like to bring up is that we're
looking at aging mice hearts. And we did
see improvements with 1213 diehome, but
these results have not been investigated
in humans for obvious reasons, unless
you're the kind of person to let
scientists crack open your chest when
needed. Props to you, but that isn't my
cup of tea. We do know some of this
translates to humans and both ways of
raising 1213 dihome are also generally
linked to improved health as a whole.
But it seems likely that these results
would translate. But I still wanted to
point that out. The main point here is
that your fat cells produce a fatty
molecule called 1213 dhome which
interacts with your heart cells and
improves your heart function especially
as you get older when heart function
declines. We can stimulate 1213 diehome
by stimulating brown fat through cold
exposure or even relatively moderate
exercise intensity and duration. And
speaking of reversing heart aging, there
are other ways of improving your heart
function like those I describe in this
video right here. Thanks for hanging
out. I'll speak with you over there.